A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Rural Poverty and Resources, Office Files of Norman R. Collins FA695
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Rural Poverty and Resources, Office Files of Norman R. Collins
1976-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Collins, Norman R.
Ford Foundation
FA695
1.7 Cubic Feet 1 standard box and 1 document box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series by file type.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Subject Files, 1976-1990
Series II. Correspondence Files, 1988-1992
Scope and Contents
Contains subject files and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Beginning in the 1950s, the Ford Foundation has provided funds to improve the management of land and water, to strengthen policy making for the rural sector and to generate off-farm employment and income, especially for women. In addition, the Foundation supports efforts to increase the productivity of agriculture and to strengthen rural development organizations.
Biographical / Historical
Norman Collins (1928-2019) established a career in agricultural research that centered on food security and poverty reduction. Collins worked for 30 years at the Ford Foundation. In 1969, he joined the Foundation as a Program Advisor in the Latin America and the Caribbean, Chile Program. He then worked in the larger Latin America and the Caribbean Program for several years before moving to the Asia and the Pacific, India Program. From the late 1980s to the early 1990s, he led the Foundation's Rural Poverty and Resources Program as Program Officer in Charge and then Director. After that position, he became the Foundation's Representative to Mexico and Central America. Collins' last assignment at the Foundation was as Director of the Special Project on Program Information Technology in the Office of Organizational Services. Collins retired from the Foundation in 2000.
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Collins was a professor of agricultural economics and business administration at the University of California at Berkeley. A collaborative program between UC and Chile enabled him to work for several years as a visiting professor at the University of Chile.
Collins earned a B.A. from Kansas State University and a master's and doctorate in economics from Harvard University. During the Korean War, he served in the United States Air Force. Collins died in 2019.
- Subject Files, 1976-1990; I
  - Poland, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Foundation for the Development of Polish Agriculture, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - IMMI External Review, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Individual Grants, 1976-1989 (Box 1)
  - Designated Authority Grants -- FY 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - New Staff Orientation Program, 1987 March 11 (Box 1)
  - AAEA Foundation, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Management Information Systems Steering Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - International Association of Agricultural Economists, 1982-1990 (Box 1)
  - Fund for the International Conference on Agricultural Economists, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Files, 1988-1992; II
  - Rural Poverty and Resources Circulating Chronological Correspondence File, 1991 October-1992 March (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 January (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 February (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 March (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 April (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 May-June (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 July-August (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 September (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 October (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 November (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1988 December (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 January (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 February (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 March (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 April (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 May (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 June (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 July (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 August (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron File, 1989 September (Box 1)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1989 October (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1989 November (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1989 December (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 January (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 February (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 March (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 April (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 May (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 June (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 October (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 November (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1990 December (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1991 January (Box 2)
  - NRC Chron Files, 1991 February-March (Box 2)